Right, בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*. So today's דף *daf* is officially ס"ד
*Samech Dalet*, 64. We start on ס"ג *Samech Gimmel*, and we pick
up here on the משנה Mishna. *mishna*, towards the bottom of ס"ג
עמוד א Samech Gimmel Amud Aleph, *Samech Gimmel Amud Aleph*. So let's
take a look. המורדת על בעלה *Hamoredet al ba'alah*, a woman, now
we move from a משנה Mishna. *mishna* that discussed, that discussed עונה
*onah*, the husband's obligation in terms of sex at regular intervals,
and we discussed that the משנה Mishnah, *mishna* frames it in terms
of at a certain frequency. There's other ways of framing it, maybe
that was only רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* position, we'll bracket, we'll put
that at the back burner for now. And then we had a
whole fascinating passage in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* about the tension between
תלמוד תורה Torah. *Talmud Torah* and a man's responsibility of עונה *onah*
or responsibility at home. Now we move back to this issue of
the range of responsibilities of wife to husband, husband to wife. So,
and this now talks about somebody who is not living up to
his or her responsibilities, which is the keyword of מורדת moredes *moredet*,
or what occurs less commonly מורד mored *mored*, if he's not living
up to his responsibilities, and how that is dealt with. And this
becomes a passage we're going to be looking at which has extremely
practical in terms of the implications both for עגונה aguna *agunah* issues
and in general in terms of attitudes towards the rabbi's responsibility towards
a marriage that's not working out as it should. So let's take
a look. המורדת על בעלה *Hamoredet al ba'alah*, a woman who is
rebelling against her husband, not living up to her responsibility, not exactly
clear what it's referring to because until now we've dealt only with
one responsibility that she has, which is doing the domestic work. It
spoke about his obligation towards her in terms of sex at a
certain frequency, did not speak about her obligation to him in that
regard. So right now the only thing explicitly that we've focused on
is her doing her domestic duties, in terms of the מעשה ידיים
*ma'aseh yadayim*. So we'll see in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* how they
frame what exactly area she is being מורדת moredes *moredet* from. But
המורדת *a moredet*, a woman who is rebelling, not doing her domestic
responsibilities על בעלה *al ba'alah*, פוחתין לה מכתובתה *pofsin lach mi-ktuvatah*. So
we try to compel or influence her to
change her ways through deducting her כתובה kesuvah. *ktuva*, through a monetary
fine. So basically what we're going to do is for each week
that she is remaining in this status of מורדת moredet. *moredet* and
refusing to do her responsibility, the value of her כתובה kesuvah *ktuva*
will go down. Now remember the total value of the כתובה kesuvah
*ktuva* is the base amount, 100 or the 200 זוז *zuz*, plus
whatever תוספת *tosefet* he added, plus the value of the property that
she brought in, her dowry, her, right? So all of those are
the, all of that is the total value of the כתובה kesuvah?
*ktuva*. If we slowly reduce it, maybe it's worth $10,000. Maybe the
200 זוז *zuz* is worth $2,000 and she brought in a big
dowry and that's $7,000 and he added a תוספת *tosefet* that's another
1,000, maybe it's $10,000. We're going to slowly reduce it week by
week so that even if she basically changes her ways and starts
doing her domestic responsibilities, she's going to be out that money, because
if she does get divorced or if he actually does die, she's
now not going to be able to collect the full value of
the כתובה kesuvah *ktuva*, she'll only be able to collect 9,000 or
5,000 depending on how long things have been going this way and
us continuing to fine her on a weekly basis. Okay. So פוחתין
לה מכתובתה *pofsin lach mi-ktuvatah*, we reduce the amount of the כתובה
kesuvah *ktuva*, we fine her, שבעה shivah. דינרין בשבת *shiva dinarin b'shabbos*,
seven דינר *dinar* each שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos*. Okay, so we'll see exactly
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* exactly how the dollar values work out
and what that means in terms of its value relative to the
200 זוז *zuz* of the כתובה Kesuvah *ktuva*. רבי יהודה אומר שבעה
טרפאיקין *Rabbi Yehuda omer shiva tarpe'ikin*, six, seven טרפאיקין *tarpe'ikin*, and we'll
see what that is. עד מתי הוא פוחת *Ad masai hu pofes*?
Now how long do you keep on going in terms of reducing
the amount of the כתובה Kesuvah *ktuva*, how long do you let
this situation continue?
So עד כנגד כתובתה *ad keneged ktuvatah*, until the total value of
the כתובה Ketubah *ktuva*, until the כתובה kesuvah *ktuva* goes down to
zero. רבי יוסי אומר לעולם הוא פוחת והולך *Rabbi Yosei omer le'olam
hu pofes v'holech*, no, you even go into the negative territory, you
keep on going lower and lower and lower. So now she actually
owes him money. What good is that going to do? שאם תיפול
לה ירושה ממקום אחר *she'im tipol lah yerusha mimakom acher*, that if
in the end she ever comes into any property, any money,
so then גובה ממנה *goveh mimena*, he can collect from her. So
it's not just reducing her כתובה kesuvah *ktuva* amount, you can even,
she can even incur a debt to the husband that she'll owe
him money even if at some later time she comes into that
type of money. וכן *V'chen*, and so that's if she does not
live up to her responsibility to him. וכן המורד על אשתו v'chein
hamored al ishto
now let's say he's not living up to his responsibility to her
מוסיפין על כתובתה mosifin al kesuvatah then you increase the amount of
כתובה. kesuvah So it's similar right neither of these impacts are felt
immediately because you know it's only felt at a time when the
כתובה kesuvah, would be payable both her loss and his loss. So
here what you do is you increase the כתובה kesuvah, amount it
was worth $10,000 each week that he's not living up to his
responsibility the amount increases. How much does it increase? שלושה דינרים בשבת
sheloshah dinarim b'shabbos less than half. The impact to him is less
than half than the impact to her. For her it was seven
dinar for him it's שלושה דינרים בשבת. sheloshah dinarim b'shabbos. ר' יהודה
אומר שלושה טרפעיקין Rabbi Yehudah omer sheloshah tarpeikin three טרפעיקין tarpeikin so
we'll again as opposed to שבעה. So we'll see why that is
why the fine the way we fine him penalize him is different
than the way we do it for her. But the first important
issue the גמרא Gemara wants to get to before we talk about
you know using these monetary fines as a way of changing behavior
is the is what is it that she is not doing? מורדת
ממה? moredes mimah? What area is she not living up to? רב
הונא אמר מתשמיש המיטה Rav Huna amar mi-tashmish hamitah she's refusing to
have sex. And again that's interesting because we've never said until now
that he's obligated to have sex with the husband that's taken for
granted. If we speak about his obligation to have regular sex with
her we're sort of taking for granted her obligation to have sex
with him and therefore that's what she's not doing. ר' יוסי בר
חנינא אמר ממלאכה Rabbi Yose bar Chanina amar mim'lachah no she's not
doing her domestic chores or you know regular duties that we detailed
at much greater length in the previous משנה. mishna, Now תוספות Tosafos
makes a very important point and he says what's at the core
of this debate? Right I mean why don't we just assume yeah
I mean all that stuff was all that stuff was user-friendly but
it's totally fine. Okay there's also paper over there if you want
to be פרום frum us. So anyway
well
here you can use you can use my totally כשר לפסח kasher
l'Pesach mug it's somewhere here. Okay what here this one was actually
bought for פסח. Pesach. Oh no it's got water in it. Okay
fine anyway. All right so sorry. So so תוספות
Tosafos says what's at the core of this debate? I mean why
don't we say either way whatever responsibility she's not living up to.
So might be some responsibilities thank you are not are not significant
enough to warrant this type of penalizing you know not living up
to them. But the other issue תוספות Tosafos says is remember we
had the opinion before that a woman is entitled to say I'm
not going to do my domestic responsibilities and you can keep your
מזונות mezonos right יכולה אשה שתאמר לבעלה איני ניזונת ואיני עושה. yacholah
ishah shetomar l'baalah eini nizonas v'eini osah.
So תוספות Tosafos says maybe that's at the core of the debate
that רב הונא Rav Huna maybe says the only thing she can
be rebelling about is sex because if she's rebelling against her מעשה
ידיה maaseh yadeha that's not rebelling she's entitled to say I'm going
to keep my מעשה ידיה maaseh yadeha you go ahead and you
keep your מזונות mezonos and I'll keep my מעשה ידיה. maaseh yadeha.
So the only thing she can be rebelling against is sex. Whereas
ר' יוסי בר חנינא Rabbi Yose bar Chanina is saying no it's
the husband's right to say I'm not going to feed you and
don't do your מעשה ידיה maaseh yadeha it's not the woman's right.
So even so if she says I'm not doing my domestic duties
even if she says you can keep your מזונות mezonos that's still
a מורדת moredet. she's still rebelling. Okay so תוספות Tosafos says it's
possible the debate here is exactly the issue before of whether a
woman is entitled to say I am not I am not going
to do my you know you're not I'm not going to give
you my מעשה ידיה maaseh yadeha you don't give me my מזונות.
mezonos. Okay so that's the debate. Now we're going to see which
one fits into the משנה. mishna תנן Tnan וכן המורד על אשתו
similarly somebody who rebels against his wife. So what would be the
scenario of a man rebelling against his wife in parallel? בשלמא למאן
דאמר מתשמיש Bishlama l'man d'amar mi-tashmish if she's not having sex with
him לחי lechayai then we can understand the parallel. He's not having
sex with her. אלא למאן דאמר ממלאכה Ela l'man d'amar mim'lachah
if she's refusing to do her domestic duties and if that's considered
to be a מורדת moredet she's not entitled to refuse to do
her domestic duties so מי משועבד לה? mi meshubad lah? Since when
does he have to do any work for her? You know what's
the parallel? He doesn't have any מלאכה m'lachah he has to do
for her. So the גמרא Gemara says אין In yes באומר איני
זן ואיני מפרנס be-omer eini zan v'eini mefarnes if he says I'm
going to refuse to feed you that's what's parallel to right what
does she get in exchange for her מלאכה? m'lachah? His מזונות. mezonos.
So if she rebels and she says I'm not doing my domestic
responsibility the parallel would be he wouldn't do his reciprocal obligation he
wouldn't go ahead and pay for her food bills he's refusing to
pay for her food bills. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says ואמר
רב v'amar Rav האומר
איני זן ואיני מפרנס יוציא ויתן כתובה. ha-omer eini zan v'eini mefarnes
yotzi v'yitein kesuvah. Doesn't רב Rav say that as soon as a
guy says I'm going to refuse to pay the food bills he
has to immediately divorce her and pay the כתובה? kesuvah. So the
גמרא Gemara says לא למימלוכי ביה בעינן. la l'mimluchi beih bayinan. Okay
yes we're going to tell him he has to give the כתובה
ksuva. but in the process of getting him to divorce her and
give the כתובה ksuva. you know that might stretch on for a
few weeks maybe we think that we can get him to change
his behavior. get him to change his behavior and during that period
that it's going to stretch on he's going to have to be
we're going to be increasing the כתובה ksuva. amount every week that
it stretches on. Now this is really so relevant and important because
it right it raises the question nowadays when issues come up I
mean they're normally not the monetary issues here but what you see
is is that there's a problem in the marriage and the question
facing the בית דין Beis Din is how much are we going
to say you know maybe we can use certain types of incentives
or penalties or whatever to get people back on track and we're
going to try to preserve the marriage and just get everybody back
on track? And at what stage do they say this is untenable
and our responsibility actually here is to break up the marr— not
break it up but you know to let the marriage you know
go the way it's going and sort of and and dissolve and
make sure that we they don't live in this untenable situation where
people aren't you know doing what they need to be doing in
the marriage and that they it's really time for them to break
up. So the question that's really like what happens nowadays a lot
is a woman will go to a בית דין Beis Din in
Israel particularly and you know it'll be really a terrible situation about
abuse or other types of things and the בית דין Beis Din
under the sort of rubric of of שלום בית Shalom Bayis is
going to say well go back and you'll work it out or
something like that right and in these completely horrific situations all because
they see their responsibility as quote unquote שלום בית. Shalom Bayis. So
here you see that's exactly you know the גמרא Gemara not as
horrific the גמרא Gemara. is trying to figure that out. We got
a couple come to us there's obviously problems in the marriage somebody
isn't doing what normally they would be doing how much do we
say we're going to try to get them to work it out
and use different types of like I said incentives and leverages to
get them to work it out or how much are we going
to say you know what you know just give her divo— just
if you can't get this if you can't sort of get where
you need to get like then just give her a divorce let's
move on. Okay so that's the גמרא Gemara actually is dealing with
this guy the guy who's not you know who's not paying for
his wife's food bills what should he be doing at this stage
should he be should we be working with him to change that
or should we be just saying just give a divorce? And in
the end the גמרא Gemara is saying is no actually we're going
to work to— we're not going to you know we're going to—
we're going to say you gotta give a divorce and we're going
to work to get that. At the process while we're sort of
getting towards that end you know maybe he'll change and then wonderful
but it's not like we're taking the long-term view about we're going
to give this a year or two years try to wait to
see if things will work out no we're going to try to
get him to give a divorce. If in the next few weeks
he's going to change his ways great but otherwise we're working to
get him to give a divorce. So I think that that you
know that that question is a huge question about what our basic
orientation is here in terms of what are we trying to accomplish
what's our sense of our of our sort of you know goal
short-term long-term goal. Now the other important thing to to notice is
that what— what does it mean when it says that he's not
going ahead and I've been framing it like רש״י Rashi is is
that he's not paying the food bills right איני זן ואיני מפרנס.
eini zan v'eini m'farnes. And that רש״י Rashi says that's the parallel
of her not doing the work because that's what she's entitled to
for her מעשה ידיה. ma'aseh yadeha. תוספות Tosafos however says that maybe
what it actually means is not I am not paying the food
bills but it means I am not going out and getting a
job. Okay so here's the question: is the husband obligated not just
to pay the food bills but is the husband also obligated to
go out and get a job?
Okay so and תוספות Tosafos points to the word we have in
the כתובה ksuva of ואנא אפלח. v'ana eflach.
So right so we know it's one thing to say you've got
the money you've got to pay the bills but let's say he
says I'm broke. Can we say okay so you got to go
out and get a job that's your responsibility of מזונות? mezonos? So
if you take a look at תוספות Tosafos באומר איני זן ואיני
מפרנס b'omer eini zan v'eini m'farnes he
says מכאן מוכיח רבינו אליהו שחייב אדם להשכיר עצמו וללמד תינוקות או
לעשות מלאכה אחרת. mikan mochi'ach Rabbeinu Eliyahu shechayav adam l'haskir atzmo u'l'lamed
tinokos o la'asos melacha acheres. You gotta go hire yourself out to
be a cheder teacher presumably that was like not considered the most
prestigious position כדי לזון את אשתו דאם לא כן מאי עניין זה
אצל מורד ממלאכה. kedei lazon es ishto d'im lo kein mai inyan
zeh eitzel mored mi'melacha. Right so the parallel is she's not doing
his work— her work, he's not doing his work. ומהו בקונטרס פירש
משום דזן ומפרנס הוא כנגד מלאכתה של אשה. u'mihu bakuntres pirash mishum
d'zan u'm'farnes hu kineged melachtah shel ishah. Okay which means he's just
not paying the bills not that he has to go out and
find work. ואני רמי דחזינא בכתובה ואנא אפלח. v'ani rami d'chazina b'ksuva
v'ana eflach. I will work. ומהו גם זה יש לדחות כמו שפירש
רבינו תם דאפלח היינו עבודת הקרקע. u'mihu gam zeh yeish l'idchos kemo
shepirash Rabbeinu Tam d'eflach haynu avodas hakarka. פירש אחרוש ואנקה ואדור את
השדה ואביא מזונות. perush echrosh v'anakeh v'edor es hasadeh v'avi mezonos. Maybe
even though I'll work the field but at least then I'll be
working for myself. אבל להשכיר עצמו אינו חייב. aval l'haskir atzmo eino
chayav. Which is very interesting. There's a difference between saying I will
go ahead and you know work the the land my own land
that maybe I am obligated to do that's what's part of paying
the food bills. But to hire myself out to somebody else to
work for someone else maybe that much I'm not obligated to do.
It's fascinating that difference. Like what's the big deal? Whether you're working
the land or whether you're going out and getting a job who
cares what type of a job? But you know presumably it speaks
about a different type of society where it's much more of a
status you know respectable to be working your own land. and to
be hiring yourself out for labor. So this is a really interesting
question: to what degree can the wife, does the wife have a
right to tell the husband, "Stop being a deadbeat, get off that
couch, go and get a job" and is that part of the
כתובה ksuva. contract, right? Okay, so what we have right now is
that she's not either having sex or doing her domestic duties, he's
not either having sex or doing his domestic responsibilities or paying the
bills or slash or going out and getting a job. And then
the question is, right, and at least by him we've seen if
he's not doing his duties, to what degree do we sort of
say we're going to give this a lot of time and slowly
see if we can get change or to what degree are we
sort of saying no, we're going to get him to give the
גט, get, but in the short period while we're working at that,
we're going to be increasing the amount, maybe his behavior will change,
but the focus is on getting him to give a גט. get.
Okay, and we're going to have a similar question about her, right,
for her as well. Do we give it the long-term view or
do we give or do we say no, we're going to get
we're going to have him give her a גט, get, you know,
and that's going to be the immediate focus? Or is the focus
going to be to slowly work with her to change the behavior?
So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara Now we're going
still try to work the proof whether we're talking about about
sex or domestic duties. מאי בינייהו למלאכה? Mai beinihayu lemalocha?
We have to we have to get his, you know, we have
to discuss it with him. It's going to take time. It's not
going to be right away, right? So since in the process of
discussing it with him and working with him, what's you know that's
going to take a few weeks but...
Okay, so let's take a look. גמרא gemara says like this. We'll
skip the parentheses. בשלמא למאן דאמר מתשמיש היינו דקתני
חולה. Bishlama leman de'amar mitashmish haynu dekatani chola. Outside, did I skip
a line? Yes, I skipped a line. No, I didn't. מיתיבי. Meitivei.
Yes, אחת לי ארוסה ונשואה, Achat li arusa unesua,
we're going to have a ברייתא Braitah we're going to quote later.
It doesn't matter whether she's an ארוסה arusa or נשואה, nesua, which
is interesting because the responsibilities don't begin when she's an ארוסה, arusa,
but if she made a declaration, like I'm going to refuse to
have sex with him once we get married, I'm going to refuse
to do my domestic duties, then that you can be a מורד
mored even though the time hasn't come yet, a מורדת. moredet. Whether
she's an ארוסה arusa or נשואה nesua ואפילו נדה ואפילו חולה ve'afilu
niddah ve'afilu chola even if she's a נדה niddah or even sick
ואפילו שומרת יבם ve'afilu shomeret yavam even if she's only a שומרת
יבם shomeret yavam and he hasn't done יבום yibbum yet. So all
those cases she could be a
מורדת. moredet בשלמא למאן דאמר, Bishlama leman de'amar, I'm skipping the parentheses,
מתשמיש היינו דקתני חולה. mitashmish haynu dekatani chola. If she's refusing to
have sex, then we understand say even if she is sick,
because you know if she's sick maybe so
so then we might say so we understand sick you might say
well she's not really up to having sex on the other hand
it's possible for her to have sex so you have to say
even if she's sick it still applies. אלא למאן דאמר ממלאכה Ela
leman de'amar mimelocha but if it's about doing the chores the real
you know heavy duties the laundry and the cooking and the baking,
so חולה בת מלאכה היא? chola bat melocha hi? If she's sick,
that's not reasonable to expect her to do. So why is she
considered a מורדת moredet if she's not up for doing the work?
So the גמרא gemara says אלא ela fine you're right. מתשמיש כולי
עלמא לא פליגי דהויא מורדת. Mitashmish kulei alma lo pligi dehavya moredet.
Fine, you're right. We're dealing
about that ברייתא's Braitah's dealing about a case of sex. And everybody
agrees that when she denies sex she's a מורדת. moredet כי פליגי
במלאכה. Ki pligi bemelocha. The debate is if she's refusing to do
the work. מר סבר במלאכה לא הויא מורדת ומר סבר במלאכה נמי
הויא מורדת Mar savar bemelocha lo havya moredet umar savar bemelocha nami
havya moredet
and the debate is whether she's considered a מורדת moredes, or not.
What's at the stake of that debate? So you could say since
that you could say again how serious is that that we're going
to institute these fines or how much will we just say you
know what well we'll hope the marriage will straighten itself out or
whatever we try to do through persuasion it's not going to be
through fines and the question is how serious is that and that
would speak to the fact about that sex is much more central
to the viability of the marriage than who's doing the domestic responsibilities.
So that's one way of understanding it, how central it is. The
other way is what תוספות Tosafot said before, that maybe a woman's
entitled to refuse to do the work as long as she gives
up the מזונות mezonot and maybe therefore it's impossible to be a
מורדת moredes about מלאכה melocha because you don't do the מלאכה melocha
fine you won't get the מזונות mezonot but you're entitled. Okay so
that's the debate. Of course now if we're talking about sex how
can it be how can it apply to cases of נדה? niddah?
How can a woman be a מורדת moredes? when she's a נדה?
niddah? So the גמרא Gemara will get to that. גופא. Gufa. Let's
go back and look at that. המורדת על בעלה פוחתין לה מכתובתה
שבעה דינרים בשבת. Hamoredet al ba'alah pochtin lah miketubatah shiv'ah dinarim beshabbat.
רבי יהודה אומר שבעה טרפעיקין. Rabbi Yehuda omer shiv'ah tarpeikin. Okay seven
טרפעיקין. tarpeikin. רבותינו חזרו
ונמנו שיהו מכריזין עליה ארבע שבתות זו אחר זו. Raboteinu chazru venimnu
sheyehu machrizin aleiha arba shabbatot zu achar zu. So the rabbis then
afterwards said you know we're not going to do this slow long
drawn out process similar to what we saw before when the husband
isn't doing his responsibility we try to get him to give a
גט get right away. If she's not doing her responsibility we're going
to say we're we don't have patience for this you know people
aren't doing their responsibilities we're not marriage counselors you know we'll give
you a brief amount of time and then we're going to do
a גט. get. Okay so מכריזין עליה ארבע שבתות. machrizin aleiha arba
shabbatot. So the rabbis said we're going to announce it for four
weeks or four שבתות shabbatot we'll see in a minute זו אחר
זו zu achar zu so it's one after the other. So for
we're going to announce you know maybe in a we'll see in
a minute where we're going to make this announcement this woman is
refusing to live up to her responsibilities maybe we'll try to publicly
shame her. Okay ושולחין לה בית דין vesholchin lah beit din and
בית דין beit din sends her a message הוי יודעת hevei yoda'at
be... to be known to you, be informed, שאפילו כתובתך מאה מנה,
she'afilu kesuvaseich me'ah maneh,
even if your כתובה ksuva. is you know a hundred מנה, maneh,
like in like a hundred thousand dollars, הפסדת, hafsadta,
you will lose it. אחת הירוסה ונשואה ואפילו נידה ואפילו חולה, achas
hi arusa v'nesuah v'afilu niddah v'afilu cholah,
so now here's the ברייתא braisa we were quoting for, whether she
was an ארוסה arusa or נשואה, nesuah, whether she was a נידה,
niddah, whether she was sick, ואפילו שומרת יבם. v'afilu shomeres yavam.
Okay? So now we have introduced the progressive monetary penalty?
Right. What we're saying is the רבותינו, raboseinu, the second opinion here,
what does it say? רבותינו חזרו ונמנו, raboseinu chazru v'nimnu,
you know, their later decision was we're not going to שלעפ schlep
it on. We're not going to do these slight slow fines over
a long period of time. It's all at once. We're replacing that
progressive thing with
the announcement and then you lose it all. Right. So right? So
you know, it's like when you have a student that has problems,
how much do you put him on like probation and go through
this whole slow period or just kick him out? This is your
last warning, you don't switch it, you're out of here. So that's
basically what we do.
We give, exactly. So we give, so whether it's because we don't
have the patience to invest in these types of things or whether
we think that it's not our role, or whether we think that
this will be more effective, you know, whether we think if people
are already at this stage that they're being מורד mored, or
מורדת, moredes then things aren't going to change over time, you know,
you give a person a very dire threat and if that's not
going to do it then nothing's going to do it. Whatever the
reason is, whether it's a strategy issue, whether it's because we see
this as our role, whether because we see this as actually an
assessment of you know where the marriage is at that it got
to this stage, we're deciding that we're just going to give a
radical sort of you know option, the nuclear option, and you know
it's all or nothing and you have four weeks to make up
your mind and else it's over and it's done with. Similar to
what we said before when the husband wasn't doing his responsibilities, we're
just going to work straight towards the גט. get. Okay? So that's
the new ruling. אמר ליה רבי חייא בר יוסף לשמואל, amar leh
rabbi chiya bar yosef l'shmuel, so we haven't dealt with the נידה
niddah issue yet. How could she be a מורדת moredes for נידה?
niddah? אמר ליה רבי חייא בר יוסף לשמואל, amar leh rabbi chiya
bar yosef l'shmuel, נידה בתשמיש? niddah b'tashmish?
So now we're going to ask it. I don't get it, if
we're talking about sex, so how could a נידה niddah be having
sex? How could she be a מורדת? moredes, אמר ליה, amar leh,
אינו דומה מי שיש לו פת בסלו למי שאין לו פת בסלו,
eino domeh mi she'yesh lo pas b'salo l'mi she'ein lo pas b'salo,
like we said before, you know, if she is basically a נידה
niddah but the woman hasn't said I'm refusing to have sex with
my husband, then fine, she's a נידה niddah right now she can't
have sex, but the nature of the marriage is one in which
they're still having sex. If she basically makes a declaration and she
says I will never have sex with my husband again, even if
she's a נידה, niddah, it's worse to be in that state of
refusing to have sex as a נידה niddah in principle, which means
even after she stops being a נידה niddah she's going to be
refusing to have sex, right? Then it is to be then just
to have that temporary state of a נידה. niddah. So the point
is she can still be a מורדת moredet now because of that
declaration that she has made, that sort of position that she has
stated, even though it hasn't become yet meaningful until after she becomes
a נידה. niddah. So it's similar to the case of the ארוסה.
arusa. The case of the ארוסה arusa also, she's not yet having
sex. But by making a statement that she's going to refuse to
have sex, that puts her in the position of a מורדת moredet?
and therefore similarly would be the case of a woman who is
a נידה. niddah. Okay?
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, of course, okay fine.
So now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר, amar, so
okay, of course the funny thing is right, like you know if
it's just words at this stage, if it hasn't been acted on,
you wonder like why it automatically categorizes her like that. You know
people say a lot of things when they're angry at one another,
right? So again, you know, you understand that it makes a difference
if somebody really is refusing even if it's not yet relevant. But
how do you know somebody's really refusing? Maybe it's just words, right?
Unless it actually becomes that she's supposed to be having sex, you
know, and then she actually really is refusing. At this stage that
she's a נידה niddah that she's saying it, it's interesting that we
already give her that status. Is there some kind of process of
like signage and עדים edim or what? How do you verify?
They bring them to בית דין beis din and it says, your
husband says you're refusing to have sex. So she could say, he's
lying. That would then be a more like a המוציא מחבירו hamotzi
mechavero case, you know, then you would certainly need proof. But she
could say, you're right I'm refusing to have sex, you know, and
she tells you why, and I'm going to tell you why. So
right, then how does בית דין beis din get pulled into that,
right? So is בית דין beis din going to, you know, but
then becomes an interesting issue because forget whether we're marriage counselors or
not marriage counselors, the question is who's at fault. Right? Whether do
we force him to give a גט get and pay the כתובה
kesuvah or force him to give a גט get and not pay
the כתובה kesuvah is all a question of who's at fault. All
these questions where she's considered a מורדת, Moredet it's because she doesn't
have justifiable cause, right? She's
just not doing her responsibilities. Okay? And we're going to get to
that in a little bit as well. And that's going to be
like the big question that's like in some ways the heart of
כתובות Kesuvos is exactly this. Is that they got to get divorced,
does he pay the כתובה, kesuvah, not pay the כתובה, kesuvah, is
you know is it sort of who's to blame for the divorce.
If she's to blame, then he doesn't
pay the
כתובה. kesuvah כתובה. kesuvah. Okay, but you're right, it's basically they're going
to court, they're saying this, nobody's contesting those issues, and the question
is what do we do about it? If people are contesting the
issues, it's a different type of a case. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: okay, so now we get to this issue about
that we've shifted gears. We're not going to do this stretched out
thing of slowly reducing it. We're going to say if he's refusing,
give a גט. get. If he's refusing, give a גט get and
pay the כתובה. Kesuvah. If she's refusing, give a גט get and
don't pay the כתובה. Kesuvah We give her four weeks. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר אמי בר חמא, Amar Ami
bar Chama, אין מכריזין עליה אלא בבתי כנסיות ובבתי מדרשות. ein machrizin
aleha ella bebatei knesiyot uvebatei midrashot. We make the announcements about her
in public places, in the synagogues and in the study halls. Again,
this is also using social pressure to shame her into it. One
wonders if we do the same if he's a מורד, Mored, right?
There are all these things that are biased against her. The fine
is higher. Now we get these announcements that are made against her.
What if he's not doing his responsibilities? Do we make similar announcements
against him? Doesn't sound like it. Anyway, so we're making these public
announcements. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, דיקא נמי דקתני. deika nami de-katani. That
also can be inferred from a close reading of the language because
it says ארבע שבתות זו אחר זו. arba shabbatot zo achar zo.
Four שבתות, shabbatot, which we read literally to be שבת, Shabbos? not
four weeks. So שמע מינה. shma mina. So why are we doing
it on שבת? Shabbos Because on שבת Shabbos, you get everybody together.
Where do you get everybody together? In the synagogues. So therefore, that's
why we're doing it on שבת, because everybody's gathered in the synagogues
and in the בתי מדרשות. batei midrashot. Okay, now we move on
with this. אמר אמי בר חמא, Amar Ami bar Chama, פעמיים שולחין
לה מבית דין. pa'amayim sholchin lah mibeis din. We actually give her
two warnings from the בית דין. beis din. אחת קודם הכרזה ואחת
אחר הכרזה. achas kodem hachraza ve-achas achar hachraza. The ברייתא braisa sounded
like it was only after the four weeks. I mean, she heard
it indirectly because she heard the announcements in the synagogue, but we
only sort of try to engage her directly, you know, at the
end. When we're basically about to get, do the divorce and have
her lose her entire כתובה Kesuvah, at the end of the four
weeks, we say be it known if you don't change right now,
he's giving you a גט get and that's it, you're out of
here, no כתובה. Kesuvah, Whereas he's saying no, no, no, even if
we're focusing on giving the גט get and we're not שלפינג shlepping
it out, we try to engage her earlier in the process. We
do try at least over the four weeks to get some change,
to see if we can get her to change her behavior. So
therefore, we actually send her in the beginning of the process. So
it's a big difference, the beginning versus the end. Right? It's not
just a question once or twice, how much postage should we have
to use? Right? It's a question about how much are we actually
seeing our role to try to change her behavior rather than just
to say like, okay, we're going to give her four weeks and
then that's it. You know, or how much do we actually work
with her during those four weeks? And that's what he says, מכריזין
עליה machrizin aleha at the beginning. פעמיים שולחין לה מבית דין. pa'amayim
sholchin lah mibeis din. אחת קודם הכרזה ואחת אחר הכרזה. achas kodem
hachraza ve-achas achar hachraza. דרש רב נחמן בר רב חסדא, Darash Rav
Nachman bar Rav Chisda,
הלכה כרבותינו. halakha kerabboseinu. רב נחמן בר רב חסדא Rav Nachman bar
Rav Chisda said we rule like רבותינו. rabboseinu. Now that could mean
we rule like רבותינו rabboseinu and we don't, sort of, שלפ shlep
it out like our משנה, mishna's a little, little bit each week.
Or the way תוספות Tosafot reads this is we rule like רבותינו
rabboseinu and
we only reach out to her at the end of the process.
We don't reach out to her at the beginning of the process.
We don't really try to engage her at all. Okay, we don't,
we don't see that as our role. What do you mean דרש
רב נחמן? darash Rav Nachman? Not דרש darash like, you know, like
דרשנינג darshaning פסוקים. pesukim. Like he announced in public. אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, האי בורכא. hai burcha. That's foolish. אמר ליה רב נחמן בר
יצחק, Amar lei Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, מאי בורכתיה? mai burchasei? Why
is that foolish? אנא אמריתה ניהליה. Ana amritah ni alei. I said
it to him. ומשמי דגברא רבא אמריתה ניהליה. umishmei degavra rabba amritah
ni alei. I said it in the name of a גברא רבא,
gavra rabba, I said it in the name of a great rabbi,
of a great person. ומאן? umman? רבי יוסי בר חנינא. Rabbi Yosei
bar Hanina. I said it in the name of רבי יוסי בר
חנינא. Rabbi Yosei bar Hanina. ואיהו כמאן סבר? ve-ihu keman savar? So
who does רבא Rava hold like, that רבא Rava says that's not
true? So כי הא דאתמר, ki had i-itmar, like it was taught.
רבא אמר רב ששת, Rava amar Rav Sheshet, הלכה נמלכים בה. halakha
nimlachim bah. We actually do engage her. And again, the way to
read this is like תוספות Tosafot reads it, which means we do
actually
send to her at the beginning of the process, at the beginning
of the four weeks, not just at the end. You know, not
just when we're actually about to go ahead and give and have
him give the גט. get. רב הונא בר יהודה אמר רב ששת,
Rav Huna bar Yehuda amar Rav Sheshet, הלכה אין נמלכים בה. halakha
ein nimlachim bah. No, we don't engage her. We make announcements in
public, we post announcements in the newspaper, but we never actually call
her to בית דין beis din and get in a conversation with
her. We're not going to get involved. We've given her fair warning,
and we're going to go ahead and then he's going to give
the גט. get. We do not actually directly engage her. Okay, so
now we now have three possibilities. One is we're really involved in
this for the long haul, a little, little bit each week, hopefully
slowly, slowly, slowly it's going to get her to change. One is
that we completely wash our hands of the situation. We make some
announcements, we give her fair warning, and then give the גט, get,
lose the whole כתובה. Kesuvah And the other is a little bit
of a middle position, which is, okay, we're going to speed up
the whole process, we're going to focus on giving the גט, get,
but at least over the month, over the four weeks, we are
going to be in conversation with her and see if we can
do something about it. So three whole positions on a spectrum. Okay,
there's also this understanding of נמלכים בה nimlachim bah as the...
Right, so I said I was reading it like תוספות. Tosafot. רש"י
Rashi reads that the נמלכים nimlochim go here, and רבא Rava's position
is actually going back to the משנה, mishna the slower version of
it. תוספות Tosafot is understanding is that the נמלכים nimlochim goes is
whether we send the message at the beginning of the four weeks
or only at the end. Correct. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. הלכה נמלכים בה. halacha nimlochim bah.
So that would be a big difference if נמלכים בה nimlochim bah
means still the four-week process, beginning and end, or does נמלכים בה
nimlochim bah mean the ongoing, you know, case of the משנה Mishna,
which could be, you know, over two years if you go by
the משנה version. רב הונא בר יהודה אמר רב ששת. Rav Huna
bar Yehuda amar Rav Sheshet. Okay,
fine. היכי דמי מורדת. Heichi dami moredet. Now, what's the case of
the מורדת that we actually are going to, you know, schlep it
out somewhat, either schlep it out to the extent of the משנה
or at least schlep it out for four weeks with or without
engaging her as opposed to something that we would do even more
immediate. So, what's the case of מורדת? אמר אמימר דאמרה בעינא ליה
ומצעירנא ליה Amar Ameimar de-amra be'ina lei u-metza'arna lei
where she basically is saying, yes, I do want to stay married
to him, but I am refusing to have sex in order to,
you know, in order to torture him. So, for whatever reason they're
in the middle of a marital dispute and she's using this as
a weapon. Okay, but she is basically not saying that she fundamentally
is not interested in living a marital sexual life with her husband.
So that would be a case where we think maybe she can
change her behavior. Right, she's doing this because she's angry at him.
She's doing this for whatever various reasons and therefore maybe there's some
traction here. Maybe there's some way that we can, you know, whether
it's working with her over the four weeks or whether it's working
with her for two years, but maybe, you know, we can actually
get her to change her behavior. So that's what we take some
time with the process. אבל אמרה מאיס
עלי Aval amra ma'is alai if she says, I find him repulsive
and I
never want to be married to this guy anymore, I refuse to
have sex, I can't have sex with this man ever. So then
לא כפינן לה. lo kaifinan lah. We don't do anything to try
to—literally the word כפינן kaifinan means force, but here it's force through
monetary fines. We don't do anything to try to get her to
change her behavior if she's in that position where she basically says
I will never sleep with this man again, then we basically say
to the guy, fine, give her a גט, get, you know, give
her a גט, get, end of story. Okay, now I want to
get back to that line because there's a huge implication about the
עגונה agunah issue. But let's just let me just read a little
bit more. מר זוטרא אמר כפינן לה. Mar Zutra amar kaifinan lah.
No, מר זוטרא Mar Zutra says even in that case we try
to change her behavior. Now, what does the changing of the behavior
mean in that case? So if you take a look רש"י Rashi
says
לא כפינן לה לשהותה אלא נותנין לה גט ויוצאה בלא כתובה. lo
kaifinan lah lish'osei ela notnin lah get ve-yotzei be-lo ketubah. So רש"י
Rashi says לא כפינן לה, lo kaifinan lah, like I said, we
just do the גט get right
away. And רב הונא—and Rav Huna the other position would say no,
even in that case we think that maybe with enough financial incentives
we can actually get her to change her behavior. Now, I do
want to say something that, again, and this gets to the issue
I was saying about, you know, בתי דין batei din trying to
say, oh, stay together, שלום בית. shalom bayit. Here's a woman basically
saying I find my husband repulsive, I never want to sleep, you
know, live with him anymore, you know, I will never, ever have
sex with him. And we're going to say, okay, but we're going
to see if through certain financial threats we can get you to
continue to live with him. Right? So that's pretty intolerable. How are
we בית דין bet din trying to get a woman to continue
to live with her husband and have sex with her husband if
she says that she finds him repulsive, if she says that she
finds it intolerable to live with him? Right? So we might be
able to get her to change her behavior, but is that a
desirable situation that she's agreeing to have sex with her husband because
she's afraid that she'll be left, you know, penniless and therefore she's
agreeing to have sex with a man that she finds completely repulsive
and completely somebody that she, you know, feels she can't live with?
So it's very hard to understand that. But like I said, sadly
some of that happens even, you know, today in בתי דינים batei
dinim in Israel that we just feel anyway we can get them
to continue living together we really don't care how she's feeling about
it. Or maybe he thinks דכפינן לה, de-kaifinan lah, maybe he thinks
that maybe actually she's just saying this and actually she could change
her attitude, not just her behavior, but she could change her attitude.
Okay? But the position of מר זוטרא Mar Zutra that even if
she says מאיס עלי ma'is alai we try to get her to
change her behavior, even in מאיס עלי, ma'is alai, is a very
disturbing one, again, unless he actually thinks that we can get her
to change not just her behavior but even her attitude. So, so
the גמרא Gemara says הוה עובדא ואכפה מר זוטרא. hava uvda ve-achfa
Mar Zutra. So now the גמרא Gemara, actually says, and look, here's
a story. There was a case that מר זוטרא Mar Zutra actually
compelled a woman to stay with her husband even in the case
of מאיס עלי ma'is alai and to start having sex with her
husband, this woman. ונפיק מיניה רבי חנינא מסורא, ve-nafik minei Rabbi Chanina
mi-Sura, and a great rabbi emerged from her having sex with her
husband, this woman. So you see, maybe we should force women to
have sex with their husbands even if they say מאיס עלי ma'is
alai because maybe they'll have, you know, children and great children like
רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina from סורא. Sura. So the גמרא Gemara. says
ולאו היא, ve-lav hi, you can't bring any proof from that. התם
סייעתא דשמיא הוה. hatam siyata di-shmaya hava. There it was some specially,
sort of, divinely assisted and ordained thing. How does the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* know that? Right, that's just how the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is
choosing to interpret that. So this is really fascinating, right? I'm going
to prove to you why it makes sense to force the couple
to stay together. Look at what happened in this case where we
force them to stay together. So based on your basic orientation and
attitude, you either say that's a great proof, we should always be
forcing the couple to stay together, or you say, you can't prove
anything from that, that was a crazy exception. Normal cases you don't
allow such a marriage to continue, right? So whether you look at
a case as a rule or as an exception, you know, as
evidence or an exception, depends on your starting off orientation. And again,
it's like really disturbing because of its practical implications to say that
we have a marriage that clearly based on what the woman is
saying, it is completely intolerable and we think that if we can
get them to stay together and get her to play along, that's
an acceptable, that's a positive solution, at least according, you know, to
רב ששת *Rav Sheshet*. Oh, but wait, מר זוטרא *Mar Zutra* in
this case where she says מאיס עלי mais alai, *ma'is alai*, there's
a distinction between forcing them to stay together and forcing her to
have sexual relations with him. Even if she stays in the house,
she can still say, I'm not going to have any relationship. What
do they have to do? Tie her down to the bed? Right,
so no,
no, the כפינן לה *kafinan lah* is through the, through the financial,
yeah, no, we're not saying no, כפינן לה *kafinan lah* is through
the financial penalties that's going to force her to agree to have
sex. But that's the כפינן לה *kafinan lah*. But she's still, we're
going to force her because she doesn't want to be left penniless
to agree to have sex with a man that she finds completely
repulsive, right? And so that's a, it's very hard to understand how
רב ששת *Rav Sheshet* could be saying that position. That's his, I'm
not רב ששת *Rav Sheshet*, who is it? מר זוטרא *Mar Zutra*.
That's his position. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so
before we go on, I have to say an important thing. So
let's go back to the other position. The other position, which is
the one we, that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, we rule like thankfully,
is לא כפינן לה *lo kafinan lah*. She says it's intolerable, מאיס
עלי mais alai. *ma'is alai*, we're not going to do anything, we're
just going to tell him, give a גט get, *get*. So here's
the question. It sounds like if we're not going to do anything,
we're not going to force her to change, so we're going to,
so we're going to presumably tell him to give a גט Get
*get*. So here's the question. Can a woman say מאיס עלי mais
alai *ma'is alai* and בית דין beis din *beis din* therefore compel
the man to give a גט Get *get*? The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
never spoke about compelling the man. It just says whether we try
to force her to change the behavior. Let's say בית דין beis
din *beis din* says, okay, she's refusing to have sex with you,
we're not going to do anything with it, you are entitled right
now to divorce her and not pay her כתובה Kesuvah, *ketubah*. And
he says, okay, but I don't want to divorce her, I want
to stay married to her. Okay, is he entitled to say that?
Right, that's a different question. She is not going to lose her,
you know, she right now will lose her כתובה ketubah *ketubah* if
you divorce her. We're not going to try to change her behavior.
You can divorce her without any penalty, she'll lose her כתובה *ketubah*
right away. Does he have to divorce her? Right? Let's say, I
don't want to divorce her, I'm happy, fine, we'll live together, we
won't have sex. And I know that I, that she won't get
a כתובה *ketubah* if I choose to divorce her, but I don't
want to divorce her. So that happens all the time, right? A
wife wants a divorce, she refuses to live with the husband, the
husband refuses to give a גט Get *get*, right? It doesn't matter
whether she's losing the כתובה *ketubah* or not. Is part of this
לא כפינן לה *lo kafinan lah* that we force him to give
a גט get. *get*? So which is not in the גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara*. So let's look at the first line in תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*.
אף אבל אמרה מאיס עלי mais alai. לא כפינן לה פירוש בקונטרס
לא כפינן לה לעמוד תחתיו אלא ella, יתן גט get, ויוציאה בלא
כתובה *Af aval amrah ma'is alai lo kafinan lah, piresh bakontres lo
kafinan lah la'amod tachtav ela yitein get veyoitzi'ah belo ketubah*. That's if
he wants to, he can give a גט get, *get*. ויש מפרשים
דכופין אותו להוציא *Veyesh mefarshim dekofin oto
lehotzi*, we force him to give a גט get? *get*. ואין נראה
לרבינו תם *Ve'ein nireh lerabeinu Tam*, דניחוש שמא עינה נתנה באחרים *denichos
shema einah nassan b'acherin* and then he gets into a long discussion
that no, maybe we shouldn't, we can't do that, maybe she's just
saying this as a way of, you know, because she's interested in
another man. So and basically that would shift the balance of power
in the, in the marriage, right? If he wants to divorce her
because he's interested in another woman, he's totally entitled. But we don't
like the idea, you know, that she just wants to divorce him
because she's interested in another man, right? She shouldn't have that power.
So maybe that's why she does it, maybe it's not really that
she finds it intolerable. So this basically, as you can imagine, becomes
a central issue about עגונה agunah *agunah*. If a woman can say
מאיס עלי mais alai, *ma'is alai* and we force him to give
her a גט get *get* with okay, she loses her כתובה *ketubah*,
but we force him to give her a גט get *get*, then
a woman basically has the power to break up a marriage anytime
that she feels she doesn't want to continue the marriage. She can
give up her כתובה *ketubah* but say מאיס עלי *ma'is alai*. And
actually this is the way רמב"ם Rambam, *Rambam* rules. רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam*
rules that if a woman says מאיס עלי *ma'is alai*, we force
the husband to give a גט *get*. The language of the רמב"ם
Rambam *Rambam* uses based on the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is אין אדם
דר בכפיפה עם נחש *ein adam dar bekhfiffah im hanachash*. You can't
force somebody to live under the same roof with the serpent. Okay,
if somebody finds their partner completely, you know, impossible to live with,
we're not going to force them to live together. And that's and
so therefore she is entitled to say that and therefore we can
go ahead and we'll force him to give a גט *get*. ראשוני
אשכנז Ashkenaz *Rishonei Ashkenaz* like רבינו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* basically disagree. And
the big issue here is for the, you know, it's huge because
that basically would, would solve the עגונה *agunah* problem if we were
to rule like the רמב"ם *Rambam*. And the response to solving the
עגונה *agunah* problem is, oh, but what about שלום בית shalom bayis,
*shalom bayis*? What about שמא נתנה עיניה באחר? shema natna eineha b'acher,
Maybe she's just using it to get out of the marriage, to
which he says, yeah, but you know, that actually presents a very
different view of marriage where the same way he's entitled to break
up the marriage, she's entitled to if she finds it intolerable. But
the response, you know, that no, no, no, the husband is the
one that has to be in control, she can't just walk out,
is language like, you know, שלום בית, shalom bayis שמא נתנה עיניה
באחר, etc., which is a lot of the אשכנזי Ashkenazi response. Now,
some actually historians believe that the reason what pushed the רמב"ם, other
than a very legitimate read of this גמרא Gemara to say this,
was the fact that women were converting to Islam in order to
get out of intolerable marriages, and therefore because once they then converted,
then is
then, you know, the Muslim community, you know, didn't recognize her previous
marriage and allowed her to go ahead and marry who she would
want. So once women were basically opting out by converting, you had
to find another solution, and therefore, you know, if you wind up
ruling, okay, בית דין beis din, will force the husband to give
a גט, that'll at least keep, you know, that'll at least solve
the problem. Essentially, it was an עגונה problem. So rather than having
to deal with the more radical solution that women had found to
convert, they came up with the solution of מאיס עלי, which is
actually a possible read of the גמרא, Gemara which also really speaks
about, you know, issues that עגונה activists speak about, which is about
when, you know, if the, you know, about how much are the
rabbis really motivated to find a practical solution and how much if
the facts on the ground, you know, were different, would they be
more motivated and come up with what, you know, halakhic options that
are available. So anyway, that is really rooted, it's not discussed in
this גמרא. Gemara. This גמרא Gemara is whether boom, you lose your
כתובה automatically, right, or do we try to like work with you
over at least some type of a period of time and try
to change your behavior? But how much does that mean that he
has to divorce her, that's not discussed and that's open, you know,
to possible, very, you know, two logical conclusions one could reach based
on this גמרא, Gemara what we do with that situation. How much
weight does the... yeah, it was trapped in the movie Gett, מאיס
עלי.
Oh, they discuss the מאיס עלי in the Gett movie? I haven't
seen it yet. No, yeah, I know I've been meaning to see
it. Yeah, it's good חול המועד Chol HaMoed watching, very relevant to
the תורה.
Yes.
Right. How much weight does the רמב"ם's position hold in contemporary discussion?
Yeah, in
אשכנז none. I don't know for ספרדים Sefardim how much they use
the מאיס עלי. But yeah, I mean, in Israel part of the
problem is that again, since בית דין Beit Din isn't sufficiently enough
motivated, they see too much of their role for שלום בית and
keeping the marriage together, even when amongst with an אשכנזי Ashkenazi פסק
psak they can use various leverages and find another things they don't
use what's the, you know, sort of the tools that are at
their disposal. Yeah, well they're perfectly willing to cite the רמב"ם as
a source when he is ruling against the interests of women. Alright.
Enough about this. Moving on. Okay, so but these are the important
issues here, right? Do we try to sort of like, so we
have all this whole range of reactions: slowly reducing the amount,
giving it a month's time, you know, being very quick about it
but at least engaging her at the beginning, or giving it a
month's time and only engaging her at the end, and then the
case of מאיס עלי, which is just that's it, you lose your
כתובה automatically, end of story, we're not going to try to schlep
this on at all, you go ahead, give her divorce tomorrow. But
then the question becomes, then do we force him to give her
the divorce? Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this: כלתיה דרב
זביד, Kaltiah deRav Zavid, the daughter-in-law of רב זביד, Rav Zavid, אימרדה,
imradah, she rebelled against her husband, against רב זביד's Rav Zavid son.
Okay, הויא תפיסא חד שירה, hava'ei tefisa chad shira, so she was
holding onto one type of a garment. So יתיב אמימר ומר זוטרא
ורב אשי, yasiv Ameimar uMar Zutra veRav Ashi, so these three were
sitting, it was a בית דין, ויתיב רב גמדא גבייהו, veyasiv Rav
Gamda gabei'u, and רב גמדא Rav Gamda was sitting there. יתבי וקאמרי,
yasvi veka'amri, they said: מורדת הפסידה בלאותיה הקיימין, Moredes hifsida belosei'ha hakayamin,
if a woman rebels and then she basically loses her entire כתובה,
right, like I guess רבותינו חזרו ונמנו raboseinu chazru venimnu that it's
not going to be a schlepped out process, after four weeks she
loses her entire כתובה, losing the entire כתובה includes even her worn-out
clothes. The husband has basically been giving her clothes, that's like the
מזונות mezonos and the כסות, kesus, okay? So those clothes so, you
know, those clothes are considered to be ultimately not really hers but
really his and she doesn't even allowed to take those out with
her. Okay, or רש"י Rashi says, actually, excuse me, רש"י Rashi says
it's not the clothes he gave her during the period, it's clothes
that she brought in when they got married, in her trousseau, in
her dowry. Okay, but bottom line is that how does it work?
So she brought in, let's say, ten thousand dollars worth of designer
dresses and whatever, so basically he takes possession of them, right, it's
like a dowry, he takes possession of them and then you write
ten thousand dollars in the כתובה. So she's entitled to take out,
if it were a normal case, ten thousand dollars in a case
of divorce, okay, or whatever is left of those clothes and then
the difference between that and ten thousand dollars. But here she lost
all of her כתובה. So losing all of her כתובה means she
has to leave all the clothes behind and she gets none of
none of their value. She she goes out penniless. Okay. What? Yeah,
maybe maybe we give her we let her keep the clothes on
her back. Okay. מרדה הפסידה בלויי דקיימי. Marda hifsidah belosai dekayami. So
she she loses even her worn-out clothes. אמר להו רב גמדא משום
דרב זביד גברא רבא הוא, Amar lehu Rav Gamda mishum deRav Zevid
gavra rabba hu, because Rav Zevid is a great person, Rav Zevid
is the father-in-law here, it's his family, מחניפיתו ליה? Machnifisu leh? Are
you going to flatter him, meaning are you going to tilt the
judgment in his favor to make her not to make her lose
her clothes? ואמר רב כהנא, Ve'amar Rav Kahana, but because doesn't Rav
Kahana say מיבעיא ליה לרבא, Miba'i lei leRava, Rava asked this question
ולא פשיט, Velo pashit, and didn't come to a conclusion. When we
make her lose her entire כתובה, does it include even the clothes
in her closet? So איכא דאמרי, Ika de'amri, some say, יתבי וקאמרי,
Yatvi veka'amri, they sat and they said, מרדה לא הפסידה בלויי דקיימי.
Marda lo hifsidah belosai dekayami. She doesn't lose her used clothes. She
can take her with her the clothes in her closet. אמר להו
רב גמדא, Amar lehu Rav Gamda, so Rav Gamda says, משום דרב
זביד גברא רבא הוא, Mishum deRav Zevid gavra rabba hu, just because
Rav Zevid the father-in-law is such a great person, top of ס"ג
עמוד א', אפחזיתו ליה לדינא לויה? Aphizisu leh ledina lavaye? Are you
going to reverse the judgment against him, meaning like ironic, like, oh,
like the rabbi said, he's you're overcompensating, right? אמר רב כהנא מיבעיא
ליה לרבא ולא פשיט. Amar Rav Kahana miba'i lei leRava velo pashit.
Rava asked this question whether she's entitled to the clothes in her
closet and it didn't come to a conclusion. השתא דלא איתמר לא
הכי ולא הכי, Hashta delo itmar lo hachi velo hachi, since it
wasn't said this way or that way, whether she's entitled to the
clothes in her closet, תפסה לא מפקינן מינה, Tafsa lo mafkinan minah,
if she actually is in possession of those clothes, has them in
her possession when this happens, we're not going to take them away
from her because maybe she is entitled. לא תפסה לא יהבינן לה,
Lo tafsa lo yahavinan lah, she's not in possession, we don't give
it to her. So when we say she loses her כתובה, basically
it only means she goes out penniless. Even the clothes that she
had brought into the marriage, she's not entitled she might not be
entitled to. Okay, now before we mentioned four weeks. Now we're going
to see a different version of it. ומשהינן לה תריסר ירחי שתא
אגיטא. Umashinan lah tresar yarchei shata agita. We actually now schlepp it
out for a year. So as opposed to going for possible years
like the משנה, or in opposed to going for four weeks, now
we're going to go for a year. ובהנך תריסר ירחי שתא, Ubehanach
tresar yarchei shata, and during those twelve months, לית לה מזוני מבעל,
Leis lah mezoni miba'al, but as an added type of a incentive
or fine, not only is the amount of the כתובה going down,
but nobody is paying her food bill. Okay, so that's an interesting
compromise, we're going to give it more time, but we're she's not
going to pay the food bill. So we're going to add an
added incentive. So you see all of these variations about how quick
we want to resolve this, how much we see this our responsibility,
are we do we think we can get them back together or
are we trying to just quickly sever the marriage and these whole
different ranges of tools. By the way, if you look back at
ס"ג עמוד ב', Samech Gimmel Amud Bet, תוספות Tosafos talks about the
post-Talmudic approach to it. So תוספות Tosafos says like this, ואינהו, Ve'inhu,
the the second ואינהו, Ve'inhu, let's take a look, the third wide
line, the תוספות Tosafos ואינהו, Ve'inhu, but it's the third wide line
within the תוספות Tosafos where he says, ומצא רבינו יהודה, Umatza Rabbeinu
Yehudah, you see that? So Rabbeinu Yehudah found בכתב רב שרירא, Biksav
Rav Sherira, in writings of Rav Sherira Gaon, שתיקנו בימיו לתת גט
לאשה לאלתר. Shetekenu beyamav latet get le'ishah la'altar. Not to wait four
weeks, not to wait twelve months, but similar to what we said
before about the husband when he's being מורד, give a גט right
away. We decided when she's being מורדת also give a גט right
away. ולא כשמעתין, Velo keshma'atin, not like our סוגיא Sugya דרב זביד.
deRav Zevid. וכתב נמי רבינו יהודה דרבנן סבוראי, Vechasav nami Rabbeinu Yehudah
deRabbanan Savorai, the Rabbanan Savorai, the rabbis who lived after the right
after the גמרא Gemara in the transition between the גמרא Gemara and
the גאונים, Geonim, תיקנו למשקל מינה מאי דתפסה, Tekinu limshkal minah mai
detafsa, ומייתי לה גיטא לאלתר. Umaysi lah gitta la'altar. So basically first
of all we take back any clothes that she might have taken
out of her closet, and we give her the גט like right
away. Okay, so we don't wait any time, immediately, and what? Get
on with her life. But also she loses the clothes in her
closet. Okay, so again, which is more compassionate to the woman? It's
not exactly clear. Like if the חז"ל Chazal are keep on schlepping
it out in an intolerable marriage, on the other hand, if she
if you do it right away and she gets absolutely no כתובה,
she leaves penniless, so then she has no chance to I mean,
it would seem one of these ideas of four weeks or a
year, especially if we engage her in the beginning of the process,
is probably the most reasonable sort of way of dealing with it.
So it is interesting sort of the radical approach that תוספות Tosafos
quotes in the name of the גאונים. Geonim. Okay, back to the
גמרא. Gemara אמר רב טובי בר קיסנא, Amar Rav Tuvi bar Kisna,
yeah, fit into her wanting to be married to somebody very quickly.
That's true. She she's not going to have any security at home.
That's true. But at least four weeks, give her some time to
appreciate the consequences. and decide whether this is what she wants. Okay.
So אמר רב טובי בר קיסנא Amar Rav Tuvi bar Kisna אמר
שמואל Amar Shmuel כותבין אגרת מרד על ארוסה Kotevin Iggeret Mered al
arusah ואין כותבין אגרת מרד על שומרת יבם. ve-ein kotevin Iggeret Mered
al shomeret yavam. So if a woman as we said is an
ארוסה, arusah, she's not even in a position where she should be
having sex, but she is declaring that she's not going to be,
then we would go through this whole process and start lowering the
כתובה and making these announcements and having the whole process begin, however
long or short that process is, but not a woman who is
just awaiting יבום. yibbum. That she's not yet in that state that
we should be doing this. So the גמרא Gemara says, "One minute.
מיתיבי, Meitivei, we said in the earlier ברייתא: braita: אחת לארוסה ולנסואה
ואפילו נדה ואפילו חולה ואפילו שומרת יבם, Achat le-arusah u-lenesuah va-afilu niddah
va-afilu cholah va-afilu shomeret yavam, that we do this whole process even
for a woman who is a שומרת יבם." shomeret yavam. So the
גמרא Gemara says, לא קשיא, lo kashya, that's not difficult. כאן שתבע
הוא כאן שתבעה היא. kan she-tava hu, kan she-tav'ah hi. The question
is whether he is saying, now here the question is also what
is the מרד mered by the תובע tove'a by the שומרת יבם?
shomeret yavam? I've been saying by the case of the ארוסה, arusah,
that the מרד mered is that she's saying when we get married
I'm going to refuse to have sex. Okay, but specifically also the
מרד mered could be in the case of ארוסה arusah or שומרת
יבם, shomeret yavam, "I'm going to refuse to go through with the
נשואין" nisuim or "I'm going to refuse to go through with יבום,"
yibbum, right? So it's not just that what I'm going to do
when we get married, I'm going to refuse to take it to
the next stage. So the גמרא Gemara says that's the case of
שומרת יבם shomeret yavam and maybe it makes a difference if it's
תבע הוא, tava hu, if he's saying, "Let's have יבום," yibbum, and
she's saying no, or she's saying, "Let's have יבום," yibbum, and he's
saying no. Okay, כאן שתבע הוא כאן שתבעה היא, kan she-tava hu,
kan she-tav'ah hi, דאמר רב תחליפא בר אבימי אמר שמואל, de-amar Rav
Tachlifa bar Avimi Amar Shmuel, תבע הוא, tava hu, if he says,
"Hey, let's have יבום," yibbum, and she says no, נזקקין לו, nizkakim
lo, so בית דין attends to him and fines her until she
can hopefully she'll agree. תבעה היא, tav'ah hi, if she says, "Let's
have יבום," yibbum, אין נזקקין לו. ein nizkakim lo. We don't listen
to her. Okay, it's not exactly clear why not, why we don't
go ahead and try to get him to change his behavior. We'll
see why in a minute in the גמרא. Gemara But when שמואל
Shmuel says we don't write an אגרת, iggeret, it's when she is
telling him that she wants יבום. yibbum. So the גמרא says, מאי
אוקימתא להא דשמואל? mai okimta le-ha de-Shmuel? So what are you saying
the case of שמואל Shmuel is when he says we don't go
through this process? בשתבעה היא, be-she-tav'ah hi, she's demanding יבום. yibbum. So
הא אגרת מרד כותבין על ארוסה? ha Iggeret Mered kotevin al arusah?
So why did he say we don't write a writ of rebellion
against, we write a writ of rebellion against an ארוסה arusah but
not against a שומרת יבם? shomeret yavam? It shouldn't be against. You're
saying that שמואל's Shmuel case is when she's demanding it and he's
refusing. So the phrase should be לארוסה מיבעי ליה. le-arusah mibei lei.
It should be "we write a writ of rebellion for an ארוסה"
arusah but not for a on her behalf but not for a
שומרת יבם. shomeret yavam. So the גמרא says, הא לא קשיא. ha
lo kashya. Okay, that's not a problem. תני לארוסה, teni le-arusah, change
the גירסא. girsa. Okay, so have שמואל Shmuel be talking about that
she's demanding, and she's demanding for an ארוסה arusah who demands, we
attend to her; for שומרת יבם shomeret yavam who demands, we don't
attend to her. So now the גמרא says, what difference does it
make? מאי שנא שומרת יבם דלא? mai shna shomeret yavam de-la? Why
when the woman is demanding that he does יבום yibbum do we
not attend to her? דאמרינן לה, de-amrinan lah, because we will say
to her, זיל לא מיפקדת, zil lo mifkadet, go, so have him
do חליצה. chalitzah. We're assuming if he's not doing יבום yibbum but
he's prepared to do חליצה. chalitzah. So fine, we're not going to
force him to do יבום. yibbum. Go ahead get your חליצה, chalitzah,
and anyway you don't have a right to demand it because you
are not commanded את פרו ורבו. at peru u-revu. So you have
less of a right to say you're entitled here than he is.
So that's why we'll force her to do יבום yibbum because he
has a מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו, peru u-revu, and not her,
very much biased towards the man. So that's why we'll force her
to go along with his demands, but not him to go along
with her demands. If that's true by יבם, yavam, if that's true,
so אלא ארוסה נמי נימא לה זיל לא מיפקדת. ella arusah nami
nima lah zil lo mifkadet. So in the case of ארוסה, arusah,
let's say she says, "I want him to move on to נשואין,"
nisuim, and he says, "No, I don't want to move on to
נשואין." nisuim. So why don't we also say tough luck to her?
If we're saying that we say tough luck to her when she
wants the marriage to go to the next stage and we say
tough luck, you're not commanded, you don't have any rights here, so
why would we make a difference between יבום yibbum and נשואין? nisuim?
By the way though, it's funny because the גמרא doesn't say he's
going to do חליצה chalitzah or he's going to give her a
גט. So would we let her remain in this limbo state, not
getting יבום yibbum or חליצה, chalitzah, not getting a גט, just remaining
an ארוסה arusah her whole life and still say to her tough
luck, you're not commanded? Hopefully no, hopefully we would say at least
give her the גט, but the גמרא isn't spelling that out. Anyway,
the גמרא is suggesting that she doesn't have a right to demand
moving on to the next stage because she's not commanded on פרו
ורבו. peru u-revu. But if so there's no difference between an ארוסה
arusah and a שומרת יבם. shomeret yavam. So the גמרא says... אלא,
what would be a case where why would we listen to the
ארוסה? arusa? דבא מחמת טענה. de-ba machmas ta'ana. She has a legitimate
claim to say why she wants him to move on to the
next stage and get on with the marriage, even though she is
not commanded on פרו ורבו. pru urvu. What's her claim? Forget being
commanded on פרו ורבו, pru urvu, she still wants children. דאמרה, de-amra,
she says, בעינא חוטרא לידא, ba'ina chutra leyada, I need a staff
for my hand, ומרא לקבורה, u-mara likvura, and a shovel for my
grave, meaning, I want children for me in my old age. Okay,
you don't need a מצוה mitzvah to say that you want children
and you're entitled to children. So if the woman says, I'm not
going to remain an ארוסה, arusa, I want you to move on
buddy to the נשואין nisu'in or to do יבום, yibum, we would
listen to her if she basically says she wants children. It doesn't
have to be that she has a מצוה. mitzvah. So הכי נמי
שומרת יבם בבא מחמת טענה. hachi nami shomeres yavam de-ba machmas ta'ana.
So שומרת יבם shomeres yavam the same we should listen to her.
So what is the case that we're not going to listen to
her? If she says she wants children, we will listen to her.
But with the יבום yibum he has the responsibility to להקים שם
לאחיו. le-hakim shem le-achiv. I understand, but if she's entitled to, I
understand, but she can't be held in limbo. She's entitled to say
she wants him to move on. Maybe he, it's an interesting question
about whether he could get her to do, whether he's agreeing to
do חליצה chalitza or not. Anyway, let's see where the גמרא goes.
אלא איידי דאיידי דתבע הוא. ella aidi de-aidi de-tava hu. Fine. Both
cases, forget it, forget the switch of the gears we did. Both
cases, he's basically saying I want her to do, you know, I'm
demanding something. In one case we compel her and not in the
other case. What's the difference? ולא קשיא, velo kashya, כאן לחלוץ וכאן
לייבם. kan lachlotz ve-kan le-yabbem. Whether he's demanding her to do חליצה
chalitza or demanding her to do יבום. yibum. What difference would it
make? דאמר רב פדא אמר רבי יוחנן, de-amar Rav Pada amar Rabi
Yochanan, תבע לחלוץ נזקקין לו. tava lachlotz nizkakim lo. If he wants
her to do חליצה, chalitza, then we're going to compel that because
we have a favor, we favor חליצה chalitza as you might remember
from מסכת יבמות Masechet Yevamos at the end of the day, we
say we prefer חליצה chalitza over יבום. yibum. So if he basically
says I want to do חליצה chalitza and she's refusing, then actually
we actually would compel that. נזקקין לו. nizkakim lo. תבע לייבם, tava
le-yabbem, if he wants to do יבום yibum and she's refusing, אין
נזקקין לו. ein nizkakim lo. We will not try to compel that
because we have a bias against יבום. yibum. So the גמרא says
מאי שנא לייבם דלא? mai shna le-yabbem de-lo? Why would we not
try to compel יבום? yibum? דאמרינן ליה, de-amrinan leh, זיל, zil, we
would say to him go, ונסיב איתתא אחריתי. ve-nasiv iteta achriti. Go
marry some other woman. Okay, she doesn't want to do יבום, yibum,
big deal. Let her remain a שומרת יבם shomeres yavam or go
do חליצה chalitza to her. Why is it any skin off your
back? She doesn't want to do יבום, yibum, go marry some other
woman. You don't have to marry דווקא davka her. לחלוץ נמי, lachlotz
nami, so therefore we also shouldn't compel her to do חליצה. chalitza.
We'll tell him, נימא ליה זיל ונסיב איתתא אחריתי. neima leh zil
ve-nasiv iteta achriti. So say okay, she doesn't want to do חליצה,
chalitza, big deal. Let her remain waiting for חליצה, chalitza, don't go
through the process, and go marry somebody else. Why do you have
a right to compel her? If you're married to a woman and
she's not doing her duties, we can talk about compelling her. You're
not married to her yet. So why should we be compelling her
to do חליצה chalitza or יבום? yibum? Go marry someone else, let
her remain in that state. What about her claim I want children
to take care of me? She is the one who's refusing. He,
whatever he wants, חליצה, chalitza, יבום, yibum, let him do what he
wants and move on. She's the one refusing, so why does he
have any rights here? It's not like you're married to her and
she's not doing what she needs to be. Let her remain a
שומרת יבם shomeres yavam if she's refusing and go do what you
need to do. אלא דאמר, ella de-amar, he's going to say, כיון
דאגידה בי, kivan de-agida bi, since she's bound to me, לא קא
יהבי לי אחריתי, lo ka yahvi li achriti, nobody is, you know,
nobody is setting me up on any dates, nobody's, you know, or
nobody's going to marry me. They're afraid that after they marry me,
I'm going to do יבום yibum and there's going to be another
wife. So הכי נמי כיון דאגידה בי לא קא יהבי לי. hachi
nami kivan de-agida bi lo ka yahvi li. So what difference does
it make whether she's refusing יבום yibum or refusing חליצה? chalitza? Either
way, he can claim, I've got to resolve this situation before I
get on with my life. So why is it that we force
her to resolve it in the case of חליצה chalitza and not
a case of יבום? yibum? Either way, he's entitled to say we
need to resolve this situation. So the גמרא says, and here's what
I was saying earlier, אלא איידי דאיידי דתבע לייבם. ella aidi de-aidi
de-tava le-yabbem. Fine. Both cases is he wants her to do יבום.
yibum. ולא קשיא. velo kashya. כאן כמשנה ראשונה כאן כמשנה אחרונה. kan
ke-mishna rishona kan ke-mishna achrona. It depends whether it's our first, the
first teaching or the second teaching. דתנן, de-tnan, מצות יבום קודמת למצות
חליצה. mitzas yibum kodemes le-mitzas chalitza. First you prefer יבום. yibum. בראשונה,
be-rishona, that was originally, שהיו מתכוונים לשום מצוה, she-hayu miskavnim leshum mitzvah,
people would do it for the sake of mitzvah. עכשיו שאין מתכוונים
לשום מצוה, achshav she-ein miskavnim leshum mitzvah, now people aren't doing it
for the sake of the מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibum. אמרו מצות
חליצה קודמת למצות יבום, amru mitzas chalitza kodemes le-mitzas yibum, we prefer
חליצה. chalitza. So basically, he wants her to do יבום, yibum, do
we compel that or not? Initially we would have tried to compel
it, not physically compel it, but through financial penalties. In the end
we decided, you know what, we're not going to compel יבום, yibum,
we actually are not so thrilled with יבום yibum and therefore if
she doesn't want to do יבום, yibum, she's entitled to not want
to do יבום, yibum, we're not going to compel it. Similarly, I'll
just end by, similarly to the discussion of a woman says I
can't live with my husband do we force her to give a
גט? This last big תוספות discusses, what if she says, he wants
to do יבום, yibum, she says I don't want to do יבום,
yibum, okay we said we're not going to like force it, how
would we force the other... She says I want him to do
חליצה, chalitzah, and he's saying no, I refuse to do חליצה. chalitzah.
How much are we going to actually and what type of measures
are we going to use to actually force him to do חליצה
chalitzah when she's demanding חליצה chalitzah similar to the discussion she's demanding
a גט because she says she can't live with him? If she's
demanding חליצה chalitzah and he says I'm prepared to do יבום, yibum,
I'm not prepared to do חליצה, chalitzah, or I'm not going to
do either, I'm just going to make her suffer, right? How much
are we going to actually force him or trick him or other
types of measures to make him do חליצה, chalitzah, similar to discussions
earlier is what are we going to try to do to make
him give a גט when she's not prepared to continue to live
with him. Okay. She's left in limbo, right? What? She's left in
limbo if he doesn't do anything. Exactly. So that's exactly...